Guide to the Records of the Harmonie Club 1852-1995 (Bulk 1860 - 1935) MS 282
New-York Historical Society
Harmonie Club records
1852 - 1947 (Bulk 1860 - 1935)
New-York Historical Society
Harmonie Club of the City of New York
MS 282
12 Linear feet (99 volumes, plus 5 oversize folders)
The Records of the Harmonie Club document a German Jewish New York society from its founding in 1852 until the middle of the twentieth century. The collection contains minutes, scrapbooks, and photos.
Arrangement
The documents have been arranged into the following nine series. The collection is arranged chronologically within each series or subseries.
Missing Title
Series I: Minutes, 1852-1995
Series II: Scrapbooks, 1869-1965
Series III: Membership Books and Candidate Registers, 1852-1995
Series IV: Visitor Logs, 1867-1921, 1977
Series V: Constitutions and Statutes, 1855-1884
Series VI: Financial Records and Annual Reports, 1857-1991
Series VII: Portrait Books, 1910-1915
Series VIII: Photographs and Ephemera, 1893-1981
Series IX: Publications, 1952, 1963-1965
Historical Note
The Gesellschaft Harmonie, later The Harmonie Club, was founded on October 16, 1852 by N. Gutman, M. Werner, H. Beer, H. Cohn, Chs. Werner, and Sigmund Werner to create a "mutually beneficial entertainment, occasional singing entertainments, lectures, etc" for recent German immigrants. The first meeting of the club was held November 8, 1852 in a rented room on Broome Street with thirty-nine members in attendence. Between 1852 and 1867, the burgeoning club was regularly moved as the membership outgrew each rented space. After this nomadic period the club purchased land at 45 West Forty-Second Street to erect a permanent location and raised enough funds to have architect Henry Fernbach design the building.
The growth of the club was supported through dues and the creation of a nomination process to accept new members. To govern the organization, the club held monthly meetings run by elected officers. During the first ten years of existence the group held balls, lectures, and other social events throughout New York City. The tenth anniversary was celebrated on October 18, 1863 with a banquet and ball attended by over one hundred and fifty members. Two years later the club was incorporated as, "The Harmonie Social Club of the City of New York" with two re-incorporations in 1867 and 1894. The first re-incorporation altered the provisions to allow the club to own property and the building on Forty-Second Street. The latter reincorporation was to change the name to "The Harmonie Club." The members continued to use the former name, Gesellschaft Harmonie, until the use of German as the official language was changed to English in 1893.
The large building erected on West Forty-Second allowed the Harmonie Club to host inhouse events, and for the next forty years the club regularly scheduled events such as dances, lectures, concerts, theatrical performances, billiards, cards, and bowling. In 1891, the Admission Committee was created, removing the task of approving and voting on new members from the general monthly meetings. The turn of the century brought several changes to the club. These changes included the first events for non-married members, declining interest in large social gatherings such as dances, and increasing property taxes along Forty-Second Street. In response to these pressures, the decision was made to relocate to a more suitable building. The club solicited donations from its members to build a new Harmonie Club House at Four East Sixtieth Street. The building was officially opened in December 1905 at a banquet attended by over four hundred members.
To meet the changing interests of its members, the Harmonie Club purchased the North Shore Country Club on Long Island in 1914. According to an April 1914 President's Report: "The trend of time is toward the country club and healthy outdoor activity. With the increasing tendency to spread the weekends in suburban surrounding, with the increased use of the automobile, and with the increased desire for outdoor exercise, especially on the part of the younger generation." After several years of renovation the country club opened for Harmonie Club members only. This arrangement was designed to both serve and increase interest in the parent organization. Over the years, the North Shore Country Club has hosted several tournaments and still operates today as a private course.
The growth of the Harmonie Club was slowed by the outbreak of World War I. This was because of the club's German affiliation and the wartime service of current and potential members. The Club supported the United States' campaign through hosting events for enlisted men and their families. In additon, fifty of the club's members served in the war effort. Following the war, the club prospered reaching a record high of eight hundred and fifty members in 1929. This number was cut in half by 1934 with the onset of the Great Depression. The Board of Governors began a large scale renovation of the building on Sixtieth Street under the expertise of architect Benjamin Morris in the late 1930's. The new facilities along with a series of changes in the club's bylaws were designed to modernize the organization and did attract a large number of new and young members. The growth of the Club was halted in 1941 with the American entry into World War II. The Harmonie Club continued to operate throughout the war and resumed its philanthropic programs from World War I, such as hosting functions for enlisted men. Following the war, the Club's membership returned to pre-Depression numbers. The Harmonie Club still exists today and regularly hosts social functions as well as educational and entertainment events.
Sources: One Hundred Years The Harmonie Club, New York: Harmonie Club of the City of New York, 1952.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Scope and Content Note
The Harmonie Club Records (1852 - 1947) consist of eleven linear feet of material. The bulk of the papers dates from 1860 until 1935 and consists primarily of minutes and scrapbooks, but also includes photographic materials, membership directories, logs, and other printed materials. The collection records the day to day club proceedings and captures the administrative functions from its founding until after World War II. The majority of the early documents are in handwritten German from 1852 until 1892. Though the founding members were almost exclusively New York Jews of German decent, the records contain little overt discussion of the Jewish American and immigrant experiences.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donation, Harmonie Club, 1970, 1989, 2012.
Bibliography
Research use of the Harmonie Club records has resulted in at least one published work:
H. Horatio Joyce, "Disharmony in the Clubhouse: Exclusion, Identity, and the Making of McKim, Mead & White's Harmonie Club of New York City," Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians (Vol. 78, No. 4), December 2019.
Receipts (financial records); Ledgers (account books); Photographs.; Bill (financial); Programs (documents).; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Jewish perspectives (New York, N.Y.); Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (State) -- History -- 1865-1950.; New York (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Annual reports.; Ephemera.; Clippings (information artifacts); Financial records.; Leaflets (printed works); Minutes (administrative records); Pamphlets.; Scrapbooks.; Austrian, Carl J. (Carl Joseph), 1892-1970; Binge, Julius; Calman, M. Elmin; Hieronymus, Carl R.; Werner, Sigmund; North Shore Country Club, Inc.
- Series I: Minutes, 1852-1995
  Scope and Contents note
  Bound ledgers of minutes run from the Harmonie Club's founding in 1852 until 1995, with gaps from the mid-1930's to the mid-1950's. The series has been split into four subseries: General Minutes, Secretary Minutes, Board of Governors Minutes, and the final subseries contains all other committee and club minutes. The ledgers are entitled by the wording on the spine followed by anything written on the cover. In the event the cover is missing or blank, the volume is listed as the subseries name. The majority of the books have additional documents stuck in-between the pages or cover; for the most part these are directly related to the function and period encompassed in the ledger. Where necessary documents have been removed from the pages, foldered, and placed in the back cover. The minutes are handwritten until 1915, but items pasted into the books are a mix of typed and handwritten document throughout the series.
  - Subseries 1: General Minutes, 1852-1995
    This subseries contains the earliest minutes of the Harmonie Club and contain a variety of financial information, membership lists, and reports. Several of the volumes have been supplemented by glued in quarterly budgets, other minutes, Tage-Ordnung (Agendas), reports from Club officers, committee minutes, correspondence, and other documents. The majority of the General Minutes are in German, but beginning in 1865 with a Tage-Ordnung there is a slow switch to English. From 1865 to the 1880s only glued in materials are in English, but by 1890 minutes handwritten in German becomes increasingly scarce. The fourth book in the subseries contains a number of notable documents including the membership laws and the legal forms required to remain operating as a social club during Prohibition. The presence of such documents from the 1920s appears to be a filing mistake.
    - General Minutes, 1852 October 16 - 1859 April 3 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1)
    - Protocol - Gesellschaft Harmonie 1859, 1859 April 5 - 1865 January 8 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 2)
    - Protocol - Harmonie Social Club of the City of New York 1865, 1865 January 8 - 1867 July 31 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 3)
    - Protocoll - 1870 Gesellschat Harmonie, 1870 September 30 - 1920 July 8 (Offsite-box 2, Volume 4)
    - Protocoll - 1875 Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1875 July 23 - 1882 October 1 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 5)
    - Protocoll - 1882 Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1882 October 22 - 1888 May 26 (Offsite-box 3, Volume 6)
    - Protocoll - 1887 Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1888 April 8- 1894 September 27 (Offsite-box 4, Volume 7)
  - Subseries 2: Secretary Minutes, 1894-1934
    The Secretary Minutes are almost exclusively in English and the majority of the information is on loose paper that has been pasted into the ledgers. For the most part the books are in good condition, but there is some yellowing of the glue that has adversely affected the paper. Only a small amount of material are archetypal minutes taken during board proceeding. Instead the ledgers capture the organization's function through committee reports, membership candidates, presidential addresses, bills, revised constitutions, and budgetary information. Includes cards with the name and dates of members who died. Starting April 1922 the ledger is switched to a ringed binder from bound pages, allowing the minutes to be typed on loose paper and inserted using a holepunch instead of having to glue in typed minutes.
    - Harmony Club Sect'y, 1894 October 18 - 1896 April 12 (Offsite-box 4, Volume 8)
    - Secretary Minutes, 1896 April 16 -1897 August 12 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 9)
    - Harmony Club Sect'y, 1897 September 9 - 1899 April 9 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 10)
    - Minutes 1899 Harmonie Club Secretary, 1899 April 13 -1901 April 14 (Offsite-box 5, Volume 11)
    - Minutes 1901 Harmonie Club Secretary, 1901 April 18 - 1903 April 7 (Offsite-box 6, Volume 12)
    - Minutes 1903 Harmonie Club Secretary, 1903 April 10 - 1906 March 22 (Offsite-box 6, Volume 13)
    - Minutes 1906 Harmonie Club Secretary, 1906 - 1909 (Offsite-box 6, Volume 14)
    - Secretary Harmonie Club, 1909 April 11 - 1912 April 14 (Offsite-box 7, Volume 15)
    - Minutes Secretary April 1912 - March 1915 Harmonie Club, 1912 April 18 - 1915 March 15 (Offsite-box 7, Volume 16)
    - Minutes Secretary Harmonie Club, 1922 April 9 - 1929 December 19 (Offsite-box 7, Volume 17)
    - Minutes Secretary Harmonie Club, 1930 January 23 - 1934 February 16 (Offsite-box 9, Volume 18)
  - Subseries 3: Board of Governors Minutes, 1915-1995
    Likely the following minutes are the Secretary's Minutes of the Board of Governors meetings. These minutes fill the time gap in the previous subseries and are identical to the last two of the Secretary ledgers in both their physical and intellectual properties.
    - Harmonie Club Minutes Board of Governors, 1915 April 11 -1917 March 22 (Offsite-box 9, Volume 19)
    - Minutes Board Of Governors Harmonie Club, 1917 April 8 - 1919 March 23 (Offsite-box 9, Volume 20)
    - Minutes Board Of Governors Harmonie Club, 1919 April 13 - 1922 March 23 (Offsite-box 10, Volume 21)
    - Minutes Board Of Governors Harmonie Club, 1956 January - 1966 March (Offsite-box 11, Volume 22)
    - Minutes Board Of Governors Harmonie Club, 1966 April - 1968 January (Offsite-box 11, Volume 22)
    - Minutes Board Of Governors Harmonie Club, 1968 February - 1969 December (Offsite-box 11, Volume 22)
    - Minutes Board of Governors Harmonie Club, 1970 January 28 - 1982 April 18 (Offsite-box 10, Volume 23)
    - Minutes Board Of Governors Harmonie Club, 1986 January - 1991 March (Offsite-box 11, Volume 22)
    - Minutes Board Of Governors Harmonie Club, 1991 May - 1995 May (Offsite-box 11, Volume 22)
  - Subseries 4: Other Committee and Club Minutes, 1915-1931
    The final subseries is comprised of all other minutes found in the Harmonie Club Collections. Most of the volumes are the records of particular committees, but only represent a short duration of their existence. Reports and recommendations made by the committees can be found throughout the previous three subseries, often glued into the ledgers. Two of the volumes are the records of clubs founded within the Harmonie Club. The Thursday Evening Bowling Club was one of many bowling clubs founded to ensure members would have exclusive rights to the alleys located inside the Harmonie Club's building on a particular night. Each club was named by the day of the week its members bowled. The Thursday Evening Bowling Clubs records include meeting minutes, membership lists, correspondence, and its own constitution. The Minutes of the Board of Governors of the North Shore Country Club is composed of typed papers inserted into a three hole binder. The Country Club was established March 13, 1914 for the benefit of the Harmonie Club members and its Board of Governors was composed of Harmonie Club officers. The minutes include budgest, expenses, renovation plans, and description of the grounds.
    - Building Committee Minutes, 1865 April -1867 May (Offsite-box 10, Volume 23)
    - Book 36 Protocoll Directoren fur Fiscal Jahr von (Fiscal and Budgetary Committee Minutes), 1871- 1877 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 24)
    - Building Committee Minutes, 1896 March 24 - 1898 February 3 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 25)
    - Committee on Site and Building Minutes, 1902 November 20 - 1905 September 21 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 26)
    - House Committee Minutes, 1906 April - 1911 October (Offsite-box 12, Volume 27)
    - Minutes Board of Governors North Shore Country Club, Inc, 1913 March 31 - 1918 November 26 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 28)
    - Gesellschaft Harmonie Aufnahme-Comite Protokolle (Harmonie Society Admission Committee Minutes), 1891 April 18 - 1899 November 29 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 29)
    - Admission Committee Minutes, 1900 - 1906 (Offsite-box 13, Volume 30)
    - Minutes Committee on Admissions Harmonie Club, 1906 April 17 - 1907 May 12 (Offsite-box 13, Volume 31)
    - Minutes Committee on Admissions Harmonie Club, 1913 September 30 - 1931 April 6 (Offsite-box 13, Volume 32)
    - Minutes Committee on Admissions, 1973 - 1987 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 33)
    - Minutes Committee on Admissions, 1988 - 1989 (Offsite-box 13, Volume 34)
    - Kegel (Bowling) Club Records, 1874 - 1876 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 35)
    - Kegel (Bowling) Club Records, 1876-1878 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 36)
    - Minutes and Records of the Thursday Evening Bowling Club of the Harmonie Club, 1899 October - 1906 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 37)
    - Kegel (Bowling) Club correspondence (Offsite-box 14, Volume 33)
      Arrangement
      This is loose correspondence relating to the Kegel Club that is foldered in a box with material from Volume 33
- Series II: Scrapbooks, 1869-1965
  The Scrapbooks compose the second largest series of the collection and are bound books organized chronologically. Each volume encompasses several years and is composed of announcements, invitations, advertisements, brochures, playbills, postcards, mailings, programs, and menus all stapled or glued onto the pages and pertaining to the Harmonie Club. An unknown person wrote notes in the margins providing dates, cost of events, addresses, and other information. Until 1903 the majority of the handwriting and pasted in ephemera are in German. Several of the books contain loose pages and where needed such items have been foldered and placed into the back cover.
  - Scrapbook, 1869 October - 1878 April (Offsite-box 15, Volume 38)
  - Scrapbook, 1878 September - 1889 February (Offsite-box 15, Volume 39)
  - Scrapbook, 1890 - 1899 (Offsite-box 16, Volume 40)
  - Scrapbook, 1899 - 1903 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 41)
  - Scrapbook, 1904 March -1910 December (Offsite-box 17, Volume 42)
  - Scrapbook, 1912 April-1914 January (Offsite-box 17, Volume 43)
  - Scrapbook, 1914 April-1915 July (Offsite-box 18, Volume 44)
  - Scrapbook, 1915 March- 1916 December (Offsite-box 18, Volume 45)
  - Scrapbook, 1916-1918 (Offsite-box 19, Volume 46)
  - Scrapbook, 1918 October 7 - 1920 April (Offsite-box 19, Volume 47)
  - Scrapbook, 1923 January -1924 October (Offsite-box 20, Volume 48)
  - Scrapbook, 1924 November - 1925 December (Offsite-box 20, Volume 49)
  - Scrapbook, 1926 January - 1927 March (Offsite-box 21, Volume 50)
  - Scrapbook, 1930 November-1932 December (Offsite-box 21, Volume 51)
  - Scrapbook, 1958 April-1960 November (Offsite-box 22, Volume 52)
  - Scrapbook, 1963-1965 (Offsite-box 23, Volume 53)
- Series III: Membership Books and Candidate Registers, 1852-1995
  The Membership Registers and Candidate Registers are composed of several bound ledgers running from the Harmonie Club's founding until after World War II. Each book is organized alphabetically using lettered tabs. Both types contain columned pages and provide each entry with a membership number, name, address, admission date, and notes. The notes sections contain various remarks pertaining to the individual. This series also includes Membership Statistics and Rosters for that continue into the 1990's.
  - List of Members, 1852 - 1871 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 54)
  - List of Members, 1859 - 1884 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 55)
  - Membership Log (by date), 1852-1908 (Offsite-box 22, Volume 56)
  - Membership Log (alphabetical), 1850's - 1920's (Offsite-box 22, Volume 57)
  - Gasellschaft Harmonie Mitglieder-Liste (Membership list), 1859 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 58)
  - Mitglieder-Liste Gasellschaft Harmonie, 1864 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 59)
  - List of Candidates, 1884 - 1896 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 60)
  - List of Candidates, 1892 - 1905 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 61)
  - List of Candidates, 1896 - 1898 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 62)
  - List of Candidates, 1904 - 1923 (Offsite-box 24, Volume 63)
  - List of Candidates, 1923 - 1947 (Offsite-box 25, Volume 64)
  - Members Ledger, 1954 (Offsite-box 26, Volume 65)
  - Membership Statistics, 1960-1995 (Offsite-box 26, Volume 66)
  - Membership Roster, 1906-1979 (Offsite-box 27, Volume 67)
- Series IV: Visitor Logs, 1867-1921, 1977
  The Visitor logs are handwritten entries of visitors to the Harmonie Club. They contain the date, name, address, who the person was visiting going to see, and any remarks. Some ledgers are arranged alphabetically by visitor while others are arranged chronologically by date of visit. Also included is the Guest Book for the Club's 125th Anniversary Party.
  - Register Zu Fremdenbuch (Visitors Register), 1867 (Offsite-box 25, Volume 68)
  - Fremdenbuch Der Gesellschaft Harmonie (Visitors Register), 1878-1883 (Offsite-box 25, Volume 69)
  - Visitor Book, 1883-1893 (Offsite-box 27, Volume 70)
  - Visitor Book, 1893-1901 (Offsite-box 28, Volume 71)
  - Visitor Book, 1901-1906 (Offsite-box 28, Volume 72)
  - Visitor Book, 1906-1909 (Offsite-box 29, Volume 73)
  - Visitor Book, 1909 - 1913 (Offsite-box 29, Volume 74)
  - Visitor Book, 1914-1920 (Offsite-box 30, Volume 75)
  - Visitor Book, 1921 (Offsite-box 30, Volume 76)
  - Guest book, 125th Anniversary Party, 1977 November 12 (Offsite-box 25, Volume 77)
- Series V: Constitutions and Statutes, 1855-1884
  The Constitutions and Statues series is composed of yearly editions of the Harmonie Club's constitution and regulations handwritten in German and signed by all active members. Three of the ledgers are titled Statuten Buch Gesellschaft Harmonie (Statutes Book Society Harmonie) and contain only one year each. The fourth is Verwaltungs Verordnungen (Administration Regulations) and maps the changes made to the governing rules over several years.
  - Statuten Buch Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1855 January (Volume 78)
  - Statuten der Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1860 April (Offsite-box 25, Volume 79)
  - Verwaltungs Verordnungen, 1867 January -1883 January (Offsite-box 25, Volume 80)
  - Statuten der Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1884 April 6 (Offsite-box 25, Volume 81)
- Series VI: Financial Records and Annual Reports, 1857-1991
  This series contains handwritten bills and receipts pertaining to the founding of the society, including expenditures to procure space, renovate the building, purchase supplies, and other expenditures during the early years of the Harmonie Club's existence. There are also account books and appraisals from later years, as well as copies of the President's Annual Report from 1951 to 1960.
  - Bills and Receipts Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1857 April -1864 May (Offsite-box 33, Volume 82)
  - Bills and Receipts Gesellschaft Harmonie, 1867 February- 1869 (Offsite-box 31, Volume 83)
  - Inventory, 1859 (Offsite-box 25, Volume 84)
  - Accounts (Membership dues?), 1893 - 1903 (Offsite-box 31, Volume 85)
  - Accounts, 1953-1960 (Offsite-box 32, Volume 86)
  - Accounts, 1957 - 1967 (Offsite-box 32, Volume 87)
  - Accounts, 1978 - 1982 (Offsite-box 32, Volume 88)
  - Accounts, 1982 - 1987 (Offsite-box 32, Volume 89)
  - Accounts, 1987 - 1991 (Offsite-box 33, Volume 90)
  - Appraisal, 1919 November 15 (Offsite-box 33, Volume 91)
  - Appraisal, 1926 May 4 (Offsite-box 33, Volume 92)
  - Appraisal, 1927 -1930, 1968 (Offsite-box 34, Volume 93)
  - Specifications, Alterations to Harmonie Club, 1967 (Offsite-box 34, Volume 93)
  - Restaurant Operations, 1948-1952, 1954 (Offsite-box 34, Volume 93)
  - Union negotiations, 1949 - 1951 (Offsite-box 34, Volume 93)
  - President's Annual Reports, 1951 - 1960 (Offsite-box 34, Volume 93)
- Series VII: Portrait Books, 1910-1915